Have you ever wondered
if there’s a natural way
to lower your high blood pressure,
guard against Alzheimer's,
lose weight, and feel better?
Well, it turns out there is!
Welcome to the
NutritionFacts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we discover how
eating a plant-based diet
offers less exposure to
the industrial pollutants
that bioaccumulate
up the food chain.
We lack robust safety data
on most of the estimated
30,000 chemicals
in wide commercial use
registered under the U.S.
Toxic Substances Control Act.
But the greatest concern may lie
in the long-banned
legacy chemicals
that continue to contaminate
the food supply
known as PLOPs-persistent
lipophilic organic pollutants.
These include dioxins, PCBs,
and insecticides such as DDT.
How do we drop the PLOPs?
Today, most DDT
comes from meat,
particularly fish.
The oceans are essentially
humanity's sewer;
everything eventually flows
into the sea.
Hexachlorobenzene is
another banned pesticide
that may be carcinogenic,
but is more evenly spread
among animal food sources,
whereas PCBs are
also mostly a fish thing.
PCBs are a different set
of banned chemicals,
once widely used
as insulating fluid
in electrical equipment.
A study of more than 12,000
food and feed samples
across 18 countries
found that the highest
PCB contamination
was found in fish and fish oil,
followed by eggs, then dairy,
then other meats.
Salmon may have
the highest concentration
(with farmed-raised salmon
having consistently higher
contaminant levels
than wild-caught)
followed by canned tuna.
But since people don't tend
to eat a lot of fish,
other meat may be the largest
exposure for most people.
The lowest contamination
was found
at the bottom
of the food chain in plants,
which can average 7 to 20 times
fewer overall PCB
and dioxin-like chemicals
compared to ocean
or freshwater fish.
That's one of the advantages
to eating more plant-based
in the modern world.
By eating from the lowest rung
of the food chain,
we suffer less exposure
to the industrial pollutants
that bioaccumulate
up the ladder.
Every year
in the United States,
billions of pounds
of slaughterhouse by-products
are produced,
the vast majority of which
are fed right back
to the farm animals,
particularly chickens,
which can recycle
toxic heavy metals
and industrial chemicals
back into the food supply.
Lead builds up in bones
and mercury attaches
to the protein
(which is why egg whites can
have four times more mercury
than do yolks).
Most of the lead
in the bone meal
passes right through
the animals into their waste,
but then producers
can take that waste-
cow, pig, and chicken feces-
and feed it
back to the animals again.
So, you can see
how the levels of contaminants
might build up in their bodies
even when the animals themselves
may be natural herbivores.
Lower pollutant levels
may help explain
why those eating plant-based
appear to be less likely
to develop
all forms of cancer combined,
but their role in longevity
is unknown.
Heavy metals such as lead
appear to accelerate
human aging,
and most population studies
have suggested
a strong association
between exposure
to higher levels
of environmental pollutants
and shorter telomeres.
However, only a few
have been found
to be significantly related
to premature death.
One such contaminant
is the long-banned pesticide
beta-hexachlorocyclohexane.
Higher levels in the blood
correlate with higher
all-cause mortality.
A study of the breast milk
from two sisters
with different dietary habits
offered a clue
on a way to lower exposure.
The levels
of beta-hexachlorocyclohexane,
as well as PCBs, DDT,
and another banned pesticide
dieldrin
were much lower
in the breast milk
from the vegetarian mother
than the milk of her sister,
who was also breastfeeding
at the time,
but included meat in her diet.
Studies of the pollutants
in breast milk of vegetarians
dating back over 30 years
have found the average levels
of some pollutants
were 50 to 100 times lower
in the vegetarians
compared
to the national average.
In fact, for the six
out of seven pollutants
they looked at,
there wasn't even an overlap
in the range of scores;
the highest vegetarian value
was lower
than the lowest value obtained
in the general population.
Chlorinated PCBs
have also been associated
with increased mortality risk,
suggesting we should
minimize exposure,
which basically means
a reduction in animal fats.
The blood of those eating
strictly plant-based diets
were found to be
"significantly less polluted"
regarding a whole series
of PCBs,
including those found
in the study
to be associated
with increased mortality,
but their lower levels
of beta-hexachlorocyclohexane
did not reach
statistical significance.
Those eating plant-based diets
have also been found
to have markedly lower levels
of dioxins in their bodies,
as well as decreased
contamination
with flame-retardant
chemical pollutants
known as PBDEs.
No surprise given the sources
of flame retardant chemicals
in the food supply.
Again, even though
the highest levels
of flame retardants
in the U.S. food supply
have been found in fish,
the primary source of intake
for most Americans is poultry,
just because we eat
so much chicken,
followed by processed meat.
For some reason, U.S. chickens
are about 10 to 20 times
more contaminated
than chickens tested
from some other countries.
The longer people
go without meat,
the lower their levels
appear to fall.
Eating healthier
can also reduce
the concentrations
of heavy metals in your body.
The levels of mercury
in the hair
of those eating
more plant-based diets
were found to be
up to ten times lower
than of those who ate fish,
but you don't know
if it's cause and effect
until you put it to the test.
Within three months
of switching
to a plant-based diet,
the levels of mercury, lead,
and cadmium
growing out in your hair
appear to drop significantly
(but build back up
when meat and eggs
are added back into the diet).
Unlike heavy metals, though,
some organochlorine pollutants
can stick around for decades.
A USDA examination
of the levels
of dioxin-like compounds
in U.S. meat and poultry
indicated a possible concern
for U.S. public health,
but really mostly for children.
The typical U.S. adult
daily exposure in meat
was well below the EPA
established safety limit.
Only children
chronically consuming
the average daily servings
of meat or poultry
with the highest levels
might exceed it.
Taking all 33
chemical pollutants in meat
shown to be potentially
carcinogenic into account,
some European toxicologists
suggest limiting
children's consumption
of beef, pork, and chicken
to a combined total of no more
than five servings a month,
so an average of no more than
like one serving of meat
every six days or so.
In Europe,
lamb is the most contaminated,
and the recommendation
calls for adults
to eat no more than
a single serving
every four or five months.
Surprisingly, as I explored
in a previous video,
the consumption of organic meat
does not seem to diminish
the cancer-causing potential
associated with the PLOPs
in meat.
All samples were found
to be contaminated
with minimal differences
between meat raised organic
versus conventional.
What can we do
to reduce exposure?
Eat high-fiber foods,
as fiber can bind
to some of the contaminants
and flush them out of the body.
Exercise, as blood levels
of persistent pollutants
have been found to be lower
among physically active
individuals,
perhaps due to sweating,
or due to a potential boost
in detoxing enzymes,
or increased clearance
through the bile,
at least in rats.
Given current
contamination levels,
"meat consumption in general...
should be
significantly modified downward,
as much
and as soon as possible,"
though until then,
consumers can reduce exposures
to dioxins and dioxin-like
compounds like PCBs
by trimming fat
when preparing meat,
and further trim
and thoroughly drain fat
after cooking.
The Best Dietary Detox
is to not tox
in the first place.
Finally today,
we look at how we might help flush
the pollutants stored in our fat
that come spilling out into our
bloodstream during weight loss.
Most persistent industrial pollutants,
like organochlorine pesticides
such as DDT and PCBs,
were banned several decades ago,
and dioxin emission
is strictly regulated.
However, we’re still exposed to these
chemicals through several routes,
the major source of which
is contaminated food,
especially fatty animal products
such as fish, meat, and milk.
When we eat these chemicals,
they get primarily stored
in our own fatty tissue
where they slowly leach out
into our bloodstream,
but better in our fat
than in our brain
or other vital organs.
Having more body fat may
actually play a protective role
by sequestering
the toxins away,
but they can come spilling
out when we lose weight.
Body weight loss increases
the concentrations
of potentially toxic pollutants
in obese individuals.
Of the 19 pollutants studied,
they all went up,
15 significantly so.
Every study that has looked at it
found increased blood levels
of toxic pollutants
accompanying weight loss
whether induced by diet
or bariatric surgery:
increases between 14 and 388
percent with a large enough loss.
The more weight that’s lost,
the higher the pollutant levels
climb because all those
chemicals stored in your fat
over all those years
come spilling out.
The theoretical concern is that
if released into the blood
at a faster rate
than they are cleared,
the levels of these compounds
could become toxic,
causing side effects, such
as sweating, headache, and nausea,
but the opposite happened when
PCB-poisoned patients were fasted.
In 1979, about 2000 people
in Taiwan were exposed
via an industrial accident
that contaminated rice oil,
leading them to have a
higher body toxicity burden
than even long-time
consumers of seafood.
But after a modified
fasting regimen,
all 16 patients they tried
it on showed improvements,
with some enjoying dramatic
relief of their sufferings,
but this was after just
a few days of fasting;
so, they couldn’t have really
lost that much body fat.
And, they didn’t measure
PCBs before and after;
so, it’s not clear they were
experiencing some sort of detox,
nor what relevance
this has for people
who haven’t been
acutely poisoned.
The initial rise in pollutant
levels in the first year
of weight loss may
eventually stabilize or fall.
Check out what
happened in Biosphere 2,
a remarkable experiment designed
to be a completely closed ecosystem,
the longest sustained
period of humans isolated
in a confined environment
on record.
But due to crop failures,
it turned
into a 2-year experiment
of calorie restriction.
They all lost about 25 pounds
in the first 6 months
and stabilized there,
and while the levels of PCBs
and a DDT metabolite
known as DDE initially went up,
they appeared to start
coming back down,
but that initial spike
is quite a jump.
That’s one of the reasons
health authorities recommend women
don’t try to slim down
during breast-feeding.
Breast is still best regardless,
but you can keep your levels lower
by not going out of
your way to lose weight
until after breastfeeding
is finished.
What can one do to help flush
the contaminants during weight loss?
One of the reasons the pollutant
levels in the biosphere subjects
eventually dropped is because
they were eating a high fiber diet
centered around fruits, whole grains,
beans, nuts, and vegetables,
and we know that fiber can
bind to these pollutants
and potentially flush
them out of the body.
So, when losing weight,
eating lots of whole grains
may be important to increase
the elimination of pollutants
while, of course, cutting down
on animal fat, including fish,
so you don’t pile on
extra at the same time.
What about just
eating some Pringles?
What was the dietary intervention
in this randomized trial
to decrease the body
burden of pollutants?
Subjects were randomized
to 24 fat-free Pringles
a day or regular Pringles.
What?! Why?
It all started with this
crazy case report of a guy
heavily contaminated by PCBs
who managed to rid himself
of 90 percent by losing
weight eating potato chips
made out of the fake fat olestra,
which doesn’t get absorbed,
and so appears to pull
pollutants out of the bloodstream
into the stool for elimination.
It works in mice, increasing the
excretion of hexachlorobenzene
30-fold and cutting the levels
in their brains in half,
but in people, the drop in PCB blood
levels with the olestra Pringles
was not statistically significantly
greater, and for some reason,
LDL bad cholesterol levels shot
up 28 points in the olestra group.
And, while olestra and drugs
like cholestyramine may absorb
pollutants and remove
them from your system,
they also may cause you
to dump fat-soluble vitamins.
So, to get the best
of both worlds,
losing pollution
without losing vitamins,
fiber-rich foods
maybe our best choice.
Instead of olestra
supplementation to detox,
why not try to not tox
so much in the first place.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
If you want to see any graphs, charts,
graphics, images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now.
Check it out from your
local public library.
And of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.